Guide to the Marjorie Welish Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marjorie Welish papers
1950-2003
1980-2003
YCAL MSS 433
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
16.12
(18 boxes)
The papers document the work of poet, artist, and art critic Marjorie Welish. The papers consist of professional correspondence, drafts of writings, notebooks, research files, course material, teaching notes, printed material, and computer disks, spanning the years 1950-2003. The bulk of the collection consists of Welish's correspondence and drafts of writings. Correspondence includes letters from colleagues, students, and friends regarding her teaching and writings. Writings shed light on her creative process and include autograph manuscript and typescrpt drafts and printed versions of her writings, including her poetry, essays, and criticism. Other papers include research notes, her notes from courses she enrolled in, her teaching notes and class material, and various printed material that she collected as part of her research.
Welish, Marjorie, 1944-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Granary Books on the Ezra Pound Archive Fund, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 18 (computer disks): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Marjorie Welish (1944-)
Marjorie Welish is an American poet, artist, and art critic.
Scope and Contents
The Marjorie Welish Papers document the work of poet, artist, and art critic Marjorie Welish. The papers consist of professional correspondence, drafts of writings, notebooks, research files, course material, teaching notes, printed material, and computer disks, spanning the years 1950-2003.
The bulk of the collection consists of Welish's correspondence and drafts of writings. Writings shed light on her creative process and include autograph manuscript and typescript drafts and printed versions of her writings, including her poetry, essays, and criticism. Correspondence includes letters from colleagues, students, and friends regarding her teaching and writings. Other papers include research notes, her notes from courses she enrolled in, her teaching notes and class material, and various printed material that she collected as part of her research.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1950-2003. II. Writings, 1950-2003. III. Other Papers, 1966-1999. IV. Printed Material, 1970-2003.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Born digital; Electronic documents; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Welish, Marjorie, 1944-
- Correspondence, 1950-2003, undated; Series I; 5; (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence includes letters from colleagues, students, and friends regarding her teaching and writings.
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  - "Solo Impressions", 1950-1999 (Box 1)
  - "Cambridge University Press", 1950-1999 (Box 1)
  - "The Howard Foundation", 1950-1999 (Box 1)
  - Regarding Terence Diggory manuscript, 1950-1999 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1989; 11 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970-2003; 3 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977-2003; 12 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1995; 7 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1999; 9 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1999; 9 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1999; 8 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1999-2000; 6 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1999-2002; 9 (Box 4)
  - Wilson, William S., undated; 14 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and email, undated; 3 (Box 5)
- Writings, 1950-2003, undated; Series II; 4.42; (5 boxes)
  Organized under the headings of poetry, criticism, and Welish's collection of essays, "Signifying Art: Essays on Art after 1960."
  This series contains drafts of poetry and criticism by Welish. Included in the files are printed materials and research notes collected by Welish during her process of writing criticism.
  - Poetry and Criticism
    - "The Annotated Here", 1950-1999 (Box 6)
    - "Begetting Textile", 2000; 2 (Box 6)
    - "Else in Substance", 1999, undated (Box 6)
    - Course preparation, "Introduction to the Arts", 1957 July (Box 6)
    - "As We Are Told Art Grows...", undated (Box 6)
    - Howard Foundation talk, 1997 (Box 6)
    - Seminar on Art Criticism for Pratt, 1999-2003, undated; 3 (Box 6)
    - Notes and unidentified typescript draft, 1991-2003 (Box 6)
    - "Every Turn, Spoken and Unspoken", undated (Box 6)
    - "Annotated Here", undated (Box 6)
    - [Untitled, loose-leaf notebook poems], 1973, undated (Box 6)
    - "Schedule 'A'", 1980-1981 (Box 6)
    - "Bordering on Skill", undated (Box 6)
    - [Untitled blue folder poetry], undated (Box 6)
    - "Extra copies," poetry manuscripts, undated (Box 6)
    - "Narrating the Hand," criticism, undated (Box 6)
    - "A Full Hand," poetry, undated (Box 6)
    - "The Incessant Silhouette," criticism, 1988 June 6 (Box 6)
    - [miscellaneous], 1971-1985, undated; 2 (Box 7)
    - "Primitive Art", 1963-1975, undated; 2 (Box 7)
    - "The Studio Visit," criticism, 1997-1998, undated; 2 (Box 7)
    - "The Annotated Here", undated (Box 7)
    - "A Word Is Beside Itself", 1997 August, undated (Box 7)
  - Criticism, 1980-2003
    - "Minimalism: Quality through Quantity", 1996 (Box 8)
    - "Encyclopedia of Aesthetics", 1996, undated (Box 8)
    - "The Studio Visit", undated (Box 8)
    - "The Sketch as Theory", 1997 (Box 8)
    - "The Sketch as Theory," "The Open Work," "Box, Aspects of," "Minimalism: Quality through Quantity", 1992-1996 (Box 8)
    - "Cy Twombly a Retrospective: press kit from MoMA", 1994-1995 (Box 8)
    - "The Sketch as Theory," "Pail for Ganymede," etc., 1983-1995 (Box 8)
    - "The Sketch as Theory", undated (Box 8)
    - "Signifying Art," proofs and "Narrating the Hand," manuscript, 1999; 2 (Box 8)
    - "The Sketch as Theory," final manuscript pages for chapters 14 and 20 and introduction, undated; 2 (Box 8)
    - Clippings of MW's articles, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
    - Panel literature, 1996-20o0 (Box 8)
    - Pratt notes, notes on "Minimalism and Excellence," AICA board notes, correspondence, 1981-1999; 2 (Box 8)
    - Magazine correspondence, 1983-2003; 3 (Box 8)
    - Coffee House Publications, 1997-2003 (Box 8)
    - "For Artists Speak", 1996-1997 (Box 8)
    - "Assembly alternative", undated (Box 8)
    - "The Pause that Refreshes", undated (Box 8)
    - "Jean Fremon", undated (Box 8)
    - "Barrett Watten", 1997 (Box 8)
  - Poetry
    - "Textile", undated (Box 8)
    - "The Lyric Lately", 2000 (Box 8)
    - "Detained by Rest", 1999-2000 (Box 9)
    - "Delight Instruct", 1999-2000 (Box 9)
  - Criticism, 1999-2000
    - "Art and Industry" (Box 9)
    - "The How and The Why" (Box 9)
    - "The Lyric Lately" (Box 9)
    - "Design for Textile" (Box 9)
    - "Here Say. Her Say. Her See" (Box 9)
    - "Harlem Hybrid" (Box 9)
    - Outline (Box 9)
    - Free verse lyric (Box 9)
    - "The Cutting Edge of Reading" (Box 9)
    - [untitled, on Simon Lee] (Box 9)
  - "Signifying Art: Essays on Art after 1960", 1999-2000
    - Correspondence (Box 9)
    - "The Studio Visit," "The Studio Revisited", 2 (Box 9)
    - "When Is A Door Not A Door?" (Box 9)
    - Richard Hennessey material, 2 (Box 9)
    - Various versions of essays, 2 (Box 9)
    - [Notes, clippings, various essays, research], 7 (Box 9)
    - David Salle material (Box 9)
    - Komar and Melamid material (Box 9)
    - Rauschenberg material (Box 9)
    - Borovsky material (Box 9)
    - Lawrence Weiner material (Box 9)
    - Martha Rossler material (Box 9)
    - "Animal Instincts" (Box 9)
    - "Placing the Artist", 5 (Box 10)
    - Rauschenberg material (Box 10)
    - Zapkus information (Box 10)
    - Three Figures in a Landscape (Box 10)
    - Architects Who Decline to Build (Box 10)
    - Pirate Jenny (Box 10)
    - Los Angeles Art and Architecture (Box 10)
    - Essays, notes, research, 9 (Box 10)
- Other Papers, 1966-1999, undated; Series III; 3; (4 boxes)
  This series contains research notes, notes from courses Welish took, teaching notes, and class material.
  - Research notes, undated (Box 11)
  - Sculpture and photography classes, 1970, undated; 2 (Box 12)
  - 20th century artists [circa 1970], 1970-1971, undated; 3 (Box 12)
  - Social studies class, undated (Box 12)
  - Modern Art History, undated (Box 12)
  - African art and music class notes and sketches, undated (Box 12)
  - Ancient Art History class, 1967 (Box 12)
  - Primitive art class notes and sketches, 1966 (Box 12)
  - Notes for teaching, 1999, undated; 2 (Box 12)
  - Art History class notes and stamp collection, undated (Box 12)
  - Perennial Wisdom Award, 2003 (Box 12)
  - Sienne Ngai manuscript, 1991 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous book production material, 1987-1998 (Box 13)
  - Richard Hennessey material, undated (Box 13)
  - Manuscripts and course preparation, 1990-1997; 51 (Box 14)
- Printed Material, 1970-2003, undated; Series IV; 3; (3 boxes)
  - "Geoffrey O'Brien and Tim Raworth Poster", undated; 2 (Box 15)
  - "American Poetry Review", 1995, 1996, 2000; 3 (Box 15)
  - Modern Hieroglyphs, 1995 (Box 15)
  - Robert Rauschenberg Art Car Essay, 1988 (Box 15)
  - VIO, 1993 (Box 15)
  - MoMA, "Vienna 1900", 1986 (Box 15)
  - Cy Twombly catalogue, 1983 (Box 15)
  - Wenk Wilson catalogue, 2000 (Box 15)
  - Tema Celeste, 1992 (Box 15)
  - New York Public Library brochure, 2003 (Box 15)
  - Graveurs et Poesie, 2000 (Box 15)
  - Coda, 1977 (Box 15)
  - Frances Barthes, 1994 (Box 15)
  - Catherine Redmond, 1988 (Box 15)
  - Crazy Wisdom, 1986 (Box 15)
  - First Festival of Literary Magazines, 2002 (Box 15)
  - Five College Inc., 1994 (Box 15)
  - Cy Twombly retrospective catalogue, 1983 (Box 15)
  - Merrill Wagner, 1996-1997 (Box 15)
  - Russell Maltz Drawings, 1997 (Box 15)
  - Jene Highstein catalogue, 1996 (Box 15)
  - ACM, 1984 (Box 15)
  - "Ulysse Fin de Siecle Poster", undated (Box 15)
  - "Denver Quarterly," proofs, undated (Box 15)
  - Burning Deck Book catalogues, 1991 (Box 15)
  - After The Fall brochures, 1997 (Box 15)
  - Art Scribe, 1986, 1987; 2 (Box 15)
  - "Semaphare: Placing the Mark", 1995 (Box 15)
  - "Marjorie Welish 6275-1," broadsheet, undated (Box 15)
  - "ArtNews", 1993 (Box 15)
  - "After the Fall", 1997 (Box 15)
  - "New Observations", 1994 (Box 15)
  - "The World", 1979 (Box 15)
  - "Poetry in Motion", 1980 (Box 15)
  - "Oink", 1985 (Box 15)
  - "(In)visible Cities", 1996 (Box 15)
  - Center News, 1999 (Box 15)
  - F.Y.I., 1999 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1994-2003, undated; 5 (Box 15)
  - 1999-2000
    - "Post-modern Poetry," (Box 16)
    - Modernist Studies bulletin (Box 16)
    - "Coffee House Press 101" (Box 16)
    - "Rain Taxi" (Box 16)
    - "The Educational Alliance Art School" (Box 16)
    - The Academy of American Poets award ceremony (Box 16)
    - Poetry Society of America (Box 16)
    - Matthew Marks Gallery (Box 16)
    - Vermont Studio Center (Box 16)
    - [announcements] (Box 16)
    - [miscellaneous] (Box 16)
    - "Hey, You Never Know," pamphlet (Box 16)
    - "The Annotated Here," cover (Box 16)
    - "Kelsey St. Press," catalogue (Box 16)
  - Books and clippings, 1970-2003; 11 (Box 16)
  - Playbills and concert programs, 1970-2003; 17 (Box 17)
- Computer media, 0.7; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted Fragile material. Reference copies available. Consult access services for futher information.
  - Cambridge without Enelmtes Signifying Art by Marjorie Welish Wordperfect 8 2/11/99, 2006-ycal-0531-g-0001; 1 (Box 18)
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Cambridge Signifying Art Marjorie Welish Wordperfect 8.0 2/11/99, 2006-ycal-0531-g-0002; 1 (Box 18)
  - Return to CIP, 2006-ycal-0531-g-0003; 1 (Box 18)
  - Essay; CV for Enterprise Spector Welish, 2006-ycal-0531-g-0004; 1 (Box 18)
  - [no label information], 2006-ycal-0531-g-0005; 1 (Box 18)
  - "PERFORMING FORM" NAOMI SPECTOR 12.96 FOR MARJORIE WELISH, 2006-ycal-0531-g-0006; 1 (Box 18)
  - [no label information], 2006-ycal-0531-g-0007; 1 (Box 18)